[Music]
and we are back live hello everybody
good day good evening good night to all
of you wherever you are it's great to be
back live
on a live show again last the last one
was recorded
so it's a great uh pleasure to be back
live with you all or let me see who all
is there with me
and
just let me know if you can see the
screen clearly once or twice it's
happened that it was all blurred so do
let me know if there's any problem right
okay let me see whole is there i can see
sports buff
asmanor ches priya prathna ayush
mohit
uh komal dragon master samarth shweta
twilight
prajwal sanatovi constant change mayur
purobi chiching
uh saumya hersh jain sarthak nil niladri
[Music]
loop sheriff and lots of people great to
see you all thank you for being here
and hopefully you're able to see the
image clearly
i hope so i don't see anyone
complaining about it so it looks like
everything is fine
so uh as usual i'm gonna pay i have
picked a bunch of questions and i'm
gonna answer them questions from the
comments and later on
if there is some time then hopefully i
will take some questions from the live
chat also um first of all a couple of
things before that first of all we have
crossed 300 000 subscribers on this
channel so thank you to all of you who
have subscribed a huge honor for me that
so many people
are subscribed to this channel and the
congratulations to all of you this is
your channel it's all
because of you that we have reached this
number so thank you so much
uh secondly uh
an update about the book and the course
last a couple of weeks ago i announced
that i'm creating a book or creating a
course and writing a book
i'd say that it will be released by the
first week of june uh there's gonna be a
slight delay i have been extremely busy
the past few weeks as you know i've been
traveling
and doing various things so there's
gonna be somewhat of a delay but i'm
gonna crank it out as soon as possible
and
have it before you very soon so just an
update slight delay but not too much
hopefully right
okay with that said let us get into the
questions and let's begin with question
number one which is what is the question
number one
it is by domur akil
the question is i am a hindu from
mauritius i don't know
from which part of india my ancestors
are from
i did hear my grand grandparents speak
bhojpuri and i want to know how we ended
up in mauritius yeah that's a very good
question lots of indians and mauritius
and lots of indians in other parts of
the world and who have been there for
well over a century so what's the story
first of all for those of you who are
not sure where mauritius is
i will
show it on the map
where is the map
here is the map if you yeah here it is
let me remove this quickly so as you
know you you all know where india is
this is india this is the subcontinent
and the nation of india now if you go
south into the indian ocean and you go
towards africa
going to find the island the twin
islands of mauritius in the reunion
so this is the island of mauritius uh it
was under french occupation for quite a
while then under british occupation and
so on so forth long story so this is
where mauritius is is and it's got a
sizeable indian population i think
indian origin people
are either the majority or close to the
majority i'm not quite sure i'm sure
the people from mauritius if any of them
are watching would know about this so
it's got a very sizable indian
population
and uh lots of people of tamil origin
lots of people whose ancestors spoke
bhojpuri and people from maharashtra as
well people from
whose ancestors came from maharashtra
and other parts of india as well
so that is the story of mauritius now
what happened how did so many indians
end up here
and let me uh
give the answer to that so this all is a
consequence a legacy of colonization
right so here we are
so this is something that happened
in
the
19th century and 20th centuries so as
you can see this is the
story of the indian indentured workers
from 1835 to 1917.
as you can see
nearly half a million
indian indentured workers which is a
nice name nice word for slave
so
450 000 nearly half a million were sent
were transported forcibly by the british
to the island of mauritius to work as
indentured workers whatever that means
it essentially means you are a lifelong
slave and you don't have any option of
going back to india
then another 450 000 nearly half a
million was sent to the caribbean region
and also to guyana in
south america
and about 150 000 more were sent to
either south africa or eastern africa
which is essentially tanzania and kenya
so these indians were forcibly
transported to these places
far away from their motherland from
their homeland by the british against
their will essentially the word the term
indentured worker is
euphemism for a lifelong slave
essentially a person who is taken
somewhere against their wish because of
whatever technical reason doesn't matter
and then they are made to work there and
they have to settle down there and live
out their whole lives there and that's
how there are so many indians in south
africa
in mauritius in the caribbean region
trinidad etc and also in guyana in
south america
and
there's been a significant indian
presence in eastern africa for for
thousands of years and the this latest
influx added to that right so people
from tanzania and kenya indians
so that in very brief
is the story
of uh what happened how did these people
end up in mauritius it is the british
who transported these indians to work as
essentially slave labor or very cheap
labor i'm sure they will be given a
little bit of money just to make it look
like you know everything is good and we
are paying them for the labor and so on
but essentially these people were
transported against their wishes
against their will
and they were made to work there and
their descendants today are they form a
sizable percentage of the population of
mauritius and the other places that we
discussed so that in brief
is the story is the history of what
happened
all right next question is by om nike
uh the question is please show us the
dry riverbed of the saraswati in the map
i'm trying hard but i'm not able to find
it exactly well if you look at google
maps it's very hard to find it because
unless you know exactly where to look
it's it's not quite visible
it kind of blends in into the
environment uh it's a little bit easier
if you look and look at google earth
because it has topographical features
which are more visible and all that but
even then it's a little hard to see so
let me show you something different
something quite different which is which
is essentially something that comes from
left field
let me share my screen once again
um let's remove the question this here
is a topographical map
of the bottom of the indian ocean
right so this this tells you what lies
below the ocean and you can actually see
you can actually it's quite visible how
the indian subcontinent migrated i mean
moved all the way from africa
and slammed into the eurasian
continent right so so let's take a
closer look at this
so this is the indian subcontinent let's
go to the western portion of the indian
subcontinent
and if you look here
if you look closely
you can see
the drainage channels of the great
rivers
and that actually is visible
under the ocean as well under the sea if
you see on the if you can see my mouse
pointer on the eastern part of india
there is the great uh ganga brahmaputra
river system that drains into the
so-called bay of bengal and you can
clearly see below the surface of the bay
of bengal on the on the bottom of the
ocean the drainage channel of this great
river system similarly in the western
part of india
you can see the drainage system of the
great sindhu river the great indus river
and there is something else out there
there is another
drainage system that is kind of visible
but there is no river that corresponds
to it or is there
it is a paleo channel it's a drainage
channel from an ancient time when there
was a river there and that kind of tells
you where the saraswati used to be where
the saraswati used to drain
into the uh
so-called arabian sea right let's take a
look at another image this is a
different image which also uh kind of
shows you that once again if you look at
eastern india you can see very clearly
the in the bay of bengal the uh drainage
channel it's called the ganga cone
and you can see it goes all the way down
to the andaman region that's how deep
and widespread the drainage channel of
the of the ganga brahmaputra river
system is and similarly over here
in the western part of india
you will see the drainage channel and
the and the so-called indus cone
but you will also see a contribution
from a river that no longer exists
so that is the ancient four five six
seven thousand year old maybe ten 000
year old drainage channel of the great
saraswati river which no longer flows
because it dried out about three and a
half or four thousand years before today
so you can clearly see it there
and that tells you where the saraswati
is to drain into the western indian
ocean
and then if you look if you
if you know where to look on google
earth
you will be able to see the telltale
story telltale science
of an enormous dry paleo channel of a
river that no longer exists today but
which existed a long time ago so that's
what i can offer you i'm we i don't have
google
uh earth installed over here on this
computer so i won't be able to show you
but i hope that i have given you a
different perspective something that you
may have not thought about so that
so that's something
i can show you right now and i hope that
was
helpful right
okay let's go to the next question
this is by the talisman i am croatian
american
and my grandfather always taught to me
that before europe our people lived in
iran and india and i always thought like
my grandparents look like indians with
lighter skin i'd like to i'd love to
know your thoughts about this but it has
always seemed true like i know i can
almost feel it in my bones very
interesting question
by
this is an old question i found it from
eight months ago but interesting
question i'm glad i found it
so
what's the truth about the people of
croatia croatia is an interesting nation
so let's let's take a look at what
google has to say about croatia let me
share google search
one second
let's go to google
and let's do a
just a random google search for the
nation of croatia and let's see let's
see what that throws up
croatia oops
croatia and let's look at the infamous
wikipedia website once again let me
remind you all that wikipedia is not
something you can trust but let's just
see what wikipedia has to show us just
to tell us about croatia let's see the
wikipedia article
blah blah blah story history and all
that let's go to etymology yes etymology
it says the name of croatia derived from
medieval latin
croatia which is a derivation of north
west slavic chromat
which comes from the common slavic
horvath
from proto-slavic something whatever
that is which possibly okay possibly
comes from the old person
that's an interesting name
now one of the things about old persian
is that it was essentially a dialect of
sanskrit
old person the old person language was
essentially an upper branch dialect of
sanskrit it was an offshoot of sanskrit
with some distortions in this in the
pronunciations and one of the signature
changes
in pronunciation was sir to her
so in sanskrit if you have a word which
which has the sound sir
old person would have the same word but
the sa becomes aha
that's why the sindhu became the hindu
in
in the old persian language
and therefore what does this
word mean just replace h by s and it
becomes saraswat
so
the word the name for croatia
comes from old persian harawat which
comes from the sanskrit saraswat or
saraswati
which tells you
that the country of croatia hrvatska
is named after the ancient great river
of india the lost river saraswati
why would the people of croatia name
their country or the land after a great
ancient indian river
maybe because they remembered that great
river from the land they came from i
mean what other explanation do you have
except for that that their their origin
lied in the land of the saraswati their
origin lay came from
the land of the saraswati
that's the only reasonable explanation
that we have there is no other
explanation that makes sense and of
course
do note the language they use over here
in wikipedia the name possibly comes
from old person
and all that
and if you go into a further article
there will be all kinds of 500 different
uh theories they have put out there just
to obfuscate the fact that the name
comes from saraswati
so um that's how it is they've got all
these different opinions and theses but
the fact is that the country's name
the country is named after the indian
river saraswati
and therefore
your grandfather what he taught you that
your people lived in iran and india
is most likely correct
right so
uh
then the word
comes from the persian old portion
which comes from the sanskrit saraswati
so most likely what that
indicates is that the ancient vedic
indians that traveled to persia some of
them eventually traveled further
westwards and they settled down in
this part of europe which is now known
as
croatia which would indicate an indian
origin to the slavic peoples you know
deep ancient indian origin to the slavic
peoples this obviously is not proven yet
there are all kinds of tests that need
to be done but this is very strong
circumstantial evidence so what you say
is
most likely indeed correct
akash says what if the u.s falls in
china becomes the global hegemon how
would it affect india and if it's worse
was does it mean that the u.s being the
biggest player right now is serving
india more or less
okay occur so that's like a couple of
questions in one
let's mean that the u.s current
superpower the sole superpower
is it serving india
more or less
you know there's a there's a saying in
chinese
the mountains are high and the emperor
is far away
what it means is that when you are far
away from the source of power you have a
certain amount of uh liberty
as to what you do and what follows what
what policies you follow and how you
live your life if the emperor lives
right next to you you have to be very
very careful
the further the emperor is especially if
there are higher mountains between you
and the emperor then you have more
liberty and more freedom to live your
life as you please as long as you don't
offend the emperor too much
what is it what am i trying to say the
u.s is half
a world away from india it's essentially
on the other side of the planet if you
take the curvature of the planet into
account
so the u.s is the global hegemon but
that's it does it mean that this this
arrangement is serving india not quite
so much
and
think about it this way if india was
right next to the us
would it be serving india
there's another country that's right
next to the u.s mexico
now everything that's happened in mexico
over the past 200 or so years has been
orchestrated by the u.s there have there
have been wars against mexico a
significant amount of their territory
has been conquered and so on
and even today whatever is happening in
mexico is
either directly or indirectly related to
u.s foreign policy
so because mexico is so close they
are affected to a much greater extent
by u.s policies because india is so far
away it is affected to a lesser extent
but the situation doesn't serve india i
mean we can just take a look at our
ancient history i mean the 20th century
history of india in global affairs to
see what i mean look at what happened in
1971 did it serve india
i mean the us was it was
on the side of pakistan they allowed the
pakistanis to conduct a genocide in
india in bangladesh which is essentially
indian territory for thousands of years
and they send their aircraft carrier to
the bay of bengal to intermediate and
coarse india into allowing pakistan to
get what it wants
did not work because the ussr also
intervened and so on
and we know other examples of what the
u.s has been
indulging in in this indian suburban
they have always
for the longest time supported pakistan
essentially financed pakistani terrorism
in india the
the ethnic cleansing and kashmir and
what not right
so uh the situation now that india and
the us are more closely
uh aligned together not allied but
aligned together in certain aspects it
doesn't really serve india beyond a
certain point the u.s doesn't want india
to rise too much not beyond a certain
point india doesn't they don't want
india to become a new threat in the
future a big player like the chinese
became eventually the americans helped
china rise and now see what happened
now china is the biggest threat to the
u.s so they don't want india to again be
the next china right
so
whatever is going on
whatever alignment we have between
between the u.s and india right now it
doesn't
serve india beyond a certain point it
doesn't serve india beyond the point
that it ceases to serve the u.s right
that's what it is now what if the u.s
falls in china becomes a global hegemon
how will it affect india well
if china succeeds
in becoming the global hegemon india
will become what mexico is to the us
today
so as like i just said the americans
took out enormous bites out of mexican
territory the whole of california
belonged to mexico the whole of texas
belonged to mexico look up look at the
history
and some part of california is still
with mexico baja california and those
regions you know
and so on so
if
china succeeds in becoming the next
superpower it eclipses the us displaces
the us and replaces the us as the next
superpower then india will be in the
same situation as mexico
is in today
right and just look at the history of
mexico over the past 150 200 years and
you will know what i mean look it up
look it up come on do some homework
so that is what india will have to
endure and suffer which means loss of
territory which means uh military
humiliation which means uh vasal state
status and much worse
right so that is what will happen to
india if china succeeds
so does it mean we want the u.s to
continue no we want a multi-polar world
a world with three or four major poles a
world in a reasonable state of
equilibrium a world with a genuine
rules-based global order not this fake
you know arbitrary rules based order
whatever they say is the rule tomorrow
they change the rule and that's the new
rules doesn't work like that they need
an actual system that is uh
that is equal and and uh
which uh
takes everybody into account so that's
what we need
okay this
saw your is
update on ranveer show 205 it was very
interesting you are well thank you ma'am
thank you very much
the question is um what's your vision
what's your definition of staying strong
to achieve peace
what should india be doing and not be
doing
uh in the coming times
so i had said and i i've said here also
on this channel as well that you can
only have peace through strength
if you are weak you can never have peace
you'll be broken apart by others and
you'll be exploited by others those were
stronger than you
peace can only be achieved through
strength p you cannot have peace through
love
and all that
you know
peaceful strength so what's my vision
it's very simple i would like india to
to reclaim its position its historical
position as the greatest economy in the
world in the greatest civilization and
culture in the world
and that can only come through strength
look at the times when india has been
all powerful and has been uh prosperous
and successful
it's always been when you know india was
unified under a strong central
leadership whether it was doing the
mauryan era the kushan era the gupta era
or the lalitha
india has done well only if it has been
when it has been strong and unified
politically unified right under a strong
central leadership
so
the vision is very clear i would like
india to reclaim its historical position
as the number one economy in the world
and the
most advanced uh scientific and
technological civilization in the world
so that can only happen when you have
long term peace for a couple of
centuries only then can a civilization
flower and prosper if you are constantly
under attack
which you will be if you are not strong
enough then you will never have this
sort of flowering than this sort of
cultural renaissance
so india needs to become economically
and militarily powerful that is the only
vision that's the only way it's going to
happen
so to achieve peace india needs to
strengthen its economy india needs to
grow its economy india in the indian
economy is currently around
three trillion dollars the gdp right
three trillion dollars which is like a
moderately
respectable economy
we need to first reach five trillion
dollars and then ten trillion dollars so
if india
grows at the rate of around seven
percent
per year the economy it will take about
15 years to reach 10 trillion dollars if
we grow at 10 it will take roughly
9 or 10 years to reach 10 trillion
dollars so what india needs anyhow is
two decades of peace at least a decade
but
ideally two decades of peace if we can
have two decades of peace
then we can
reach 10 or even 15 trillion trillion
dollars
uh the the of gdp you know our economy
if we reach that position then
essentially we are invulnerable to other
threats because we will be so
economically and militarily powerful
that nobody will dare challenge us
that's essentially where china is today
and the reason why china sees military
threats everywhere is that is because
they are militarily and territorially
territorially expansionist we
have never been that way i don't wish
india to become another china
uh an expansionist nation
all we want is to reunify the
subcontinent
on a hundred year timeline or so
because that is our ancient ancestral
territory and that that is a there is a
there is something that is a just cause
that we would like to see achieved so
that is the long-term vision india
regaining its uh historic
position which has always been its
rightful position in the world
as the greatest economy and the
number one civilization which it always
was and we don't mind sir to have a
sister civilization in china we don't we
don't wish them anything bad
but hey don't mess with us that's all
so to stay strong we have to grow
economically as your economy expands and
you have more money available you can
invest more
in the military and that's how your
military also becomes more powerful you
can modernize your military and expand
your military invest in the right things
a bigger navy a bigger space force
better various other things right
so that's what india should be doing
what should india not be doing india
should not be
we don't want internal conflicts the one
of the major problems in india is the
possibility of internal conflicts which
are essentially fomented and financed by
external factors so there is something
we need to be very careful about and
ensure that nobody is able to interfere
in our internal matters right now it's
happening
so that's something we need to
take care of in the coming years it's a
slow process it's not easy
there are certain external forces that
are way too powerful for us
and it's not like
it's not like we can shut them down
tomorrow
as we grow grow more powerful it will
have more leverage
against these these forces so the simple
solution is grow economically and grow
militarily if you grow economically you
will also grow militarily so our entire
focus should be on rebuilding the nation
rebuilding the economy we had the
greatest economy it was destroyed now we
will rebuild it we need to accelerate
that process and go
full steam at that so that's what needs
to happen
okay rahul sharma says i went abroad to
study returned after
return living my study there unfinished
i wanted to do something for india and
generate employment
after four years i successfully did that
achieved a lot sometimes a doubt will
india be actually a superpower until
2050.
will there be a civil war breaking us or
something that will not let us develop
to a significant level
because even after returning from
australia i worry if someday i have to
leave india again yes or no what's the
percentage of those chances
see there is always a chance for any
nation of something bad happening
what you can do as a nation and
especially as
the leadership group
is to
minimize the probability of such things
happening which means you that you stay
awake and you stay alert to all the
potential threats that you are facing
right now
the visible threats and the threats that
are hidden to the public there are
things happening that
we don't we cannot see right now
that we cannot even imagine right now
there are forces at play right now in
the global order that don't want india
to rise
the leadership of india wants india to
rise so there is this constant
friction
and these this interplay of opposing
forces that we are seeing at work right
now and that's something that goes on in
every large or major nation in the world
so will india become a super power till
2050 i mean that all depends on the
definition of superpower
one of the simplest definitions of
superpower is a 15 trillion dollar
economy if india grows at even 7 per
year by 2050 we will be beyond 15
trillion dollars of gdp maybe even 20.
so if things
continue just
at a moderate rate rate seven percent
gdp growth per year we will become an
economic and of course a military
superpower by 2050 for sure
so we are on track for that
the only question is will we have
20 years of peace
because we have multiple enemies look at
our neighborhood
look at the nations that sarah that that
essentially surround india
we have china
which occupies tibet therefore therefore
they are our neighbors now
the chinese don't wish india well they
see india as the major one major
obstacle in eurasia that can counter
them
and we have pakistan which is which has
been a puppet of other
a client state firstly of the us and now
it is a client state of the chinese
and
it is used to destabilize and counter
balance india right
so these are the very visible visible
threats that we are facing right now we
also have various internal threats that
are
funded financed and aided and abetted
from outside india from by various
powerful forces beyond our borders yes
and we have
various geopolitical scenarios we have
the possibility of a coming recession
the inflation is rising in so many
things so the world is always an
uncertain place and that is
so whether india reaches its status or
not
depends on the leadership we have good
leadership today we have the best
leadership in living memory
in india today
and hopefully we will have even better
leadership in the coming
years
we can see that coming on the horizon
hopefully
so as long as we have strong leadership
things will be fine
i
personally am very optimistic
i don't see a civil war breaking out i
don't see uh
the nation
breaking up
i don't see any major foreign
military misadventure against india
because we have the right deterrence
and
the major threat comes from the chinese
there's always the possibility of see
what's happening right now in china is
that there is a
the
nation is aging rapidly this one child
policy that they have had for a long
time it's now now coming back to bite
them in the backside
their nation is aging the workflow the
workforce is getting older
the economy is slowing down the
the gdp growth is slowing down
significantly
uh the numbers they are reporting maybe
even even the numbers that they are
reporting right now may be exaggerated
so there is a in stagnation of the
economy that we have that we are seeing
in many problems
many such problems and they may get
desperate and they may feel that let's
grab whatever we can
before it's too late before our economy
goes into a recession and our population
becomes too old
so that may put them in panic mode and
tempt the chinese communist party's
leadership to indulge in some kind of
military misadventure possibly in taiwan
possibly against us in india
that could be something that would be
very counterproductive for them
especially when it comes to india
because we have
the deterrent the the ultimate deterrent
which we all know about and we also have
a good position when it comes to the
military situation the military just
bought in tibet and in the himalayan
region
so i
am optimistic
we have the right things in place more
or less
all we need is to make sure that
everyone knows that we are willing to do
whatever it takes to defend our country
and hopefully we can have 10 15 20 years
of peace if we have that then peace is
essentially guaranteed because we'll be
too too big
to uh essentially take any chances
against
so the next decade is critical
and beyond that the
forthcoming decade the 2030s will also
be very important for us but what's
important for us right now is the 2020s
it's the most critical decade of for
india in the past since 1947 essentially
the 2020s are the most important decade
for india since 1947 since the 1940s if
we get things right now we'll be in a
very good situation
so i am not concerned about whether we
become a superpower or not right now
right now i'm not concerned about that i
right now i'm concerned about us
navigating this decade
properly we don't want to make too too
many enemies we don't want to ruffle too
many feathers we want to keep our heads
down keep quiet and work and build up
our economy
first the first milestone is 5 trillion
dollars the next milestone is 10
trillion dollars we can get there in 15
years maximum if we get things right
the indian economy has enormous
potential for growth
we are just at the starting point there
is so much potential in the country
if our leadership harnesses the
potential properly and navigates the
international geopolitical minefield
prudently
we will definitely be a superpower by
2050.
so that is how i see things that's how i
see things going i am
overall quite optimistic about this
saurabh says why wouldn't anyone take
astronomical data in sanskrit scriptures
to date them
we know that most of them were correct
and they can only be recorded by someone
who and so on as it's nearly impossible
to
fabricate astronomical data after
thousands of years
that is correct that's a good question
what you're talking about is
archaeoastronomy so it's like this
the stars and the planets they move
along predictable paths in the sky
in the course of a night or a month or a
year or a century or even thousands of
years
there is even the 23 000 year old the 23
year cycle called the precession of the
equinoxes which is how the the axis of
the earth rotates
uh over time
so all of these movements of the stars
and the planets etc they follow very
clear
laws the laws of celestial mechanics
which comes from newtonian mechanics
so
it is which and because of that it's
impossible to fabricate or invent
celestial data let's say i'm fabricate
i'm writing a new text which i'm going
to claim is the old version of some
ancient text and i put in some
astronomical data in there out of my own
imagination it simply doesn't work
you can if you are an astronomer you can
tell almost very very quickly that it's
fabricated data
because today we have all these various
kinds of various softwares
that can uh
that can back date the positions of
stars and trans planets
several centuries back even several
millennia back it doesn't work with
comets and other things but certainly
for stars and also for most planets
right so it's impossible to fabricate
celestial or astronomical data
and what we know for sure is that our
ancient texts
have
an enormous amount of astronomical data
encoded within
because our ancestors were astronomers
they used to
record celestial events astronomical
events the positions of stars and
constellations and whatnot
and all of our ancient texts like the
mahabharata in the ramayana
have
astronomical data that corresponds to
various events it's it's all recorded
so therefore
it should be possible to date these
texts
based on
the astronomical data that these texts
contain
so why has it not happened many people
have tried this
many people have come up with various
claims
of the dates of the ramayana and the
mahabharata various other events
right
and they are they all have different
dates oh why is it so
the
answer is because is that
all of these
scholars
they have interpreted the sanskrit texts
differently
so when you have different
interpretations and when you calculate
the dates
based on your personal interpretation
and when somebody has a different
interpretation of the text you will
arrive at different dates
so right now what we are witnessing is
that there is a whole
cacophony going on of these various
researchers of the mahabharata ramayana
who have used the astronomical data
and
translated that from sanskrit to
whatever language works best for them
and then calculated dates and they all
have different dates and they're all
fighting amongst each other very
publicly
about who is right
so that's where we are today
lots of people have tried this and lots
of people they have all come up with
different dates
and that's where we are today so what
needs to happen is uh
each of these claims first of all this
there needs to be a proper scientific
committee of astronomers who can do the
calculation and verify all of these
claims and first of all you need
somebody who can reliably translate from
sanskrit into hindi or english or
whichever language which can then be
given to the astronomers to do their
calculations
so right now we are witnessing this
unfortunate very public fight among all
these people i don't have any per
preferred date
because i haven't checked all the all
the calculations myself it's a very long
tedious task it's not a fight that is
for me that's not my fight that's not my
task i cannot take up every single
project in the world right
so as of now uh
i don't have a horse in this race there
are multiple horses all
vying for the prime position everyone is
claimed my claim my my calculations are
right listen i don't have any preferred
person i don't have any preferred date
let's see how it goes the answers are
all there
in the texts the only problem is that
they are all translating in a different
way and that's why they're coming up
with different dates
so
so that's where we are today
so it can be done it will be done
eventually when the time is right
okay swarup idea says why does the u.s
want a ban on asat missile testing
anti-satellite missile testing for all
countries including themselves
want it hurt their own national interest
also well
why will it hurt their own national
interest
they have already done all the tests
they would want to do so it's like this
see
the americans
have been conducting anti-satellite
missile tests since the 1950s
that's when the concept first emerged
and they've been
testing this uh this
anti-satellite uh technology since the
1950s and 1960s these ussr also
did multiple tests beginning in the
1960s i believe
and there have been there have been lots
of tests conducted tests from ground
tests from ship tests from
uh air launched missiles missiles
launched from fighter planes and what
not
they have done lots of tests and
they have essentially perfected the
technology
right so that's point number one
secondly
recently more countries have tried this
out the chinese did a test i think in
2017 and something more recently maybe
the first chinese test that i remember
was from 2007 i believe
and there was at least one more test in
more recent times done by the chinese
and as you i'm sure all you're all aware
india also did a test in 2019 i believe
mission shakti which was a successful
test we destroyed one of our own
satellites
to validate the technology and it worked
so as of today as far as i am as far as
i understand there are four nations with
asap technology the us the the russians
india and china now the us and the
russians have the most advanced
technology they've done lots of tests
uh
so as far as the americans are concerned
they have kind of perfected the
technology i'm not sure if they can take
out a satellite from geostationary orbit
which is 36 000 kilometers or so roughly
but certainly they can take out
satellites from low earth orbit and
higher orbits as well
we
india we have taken out one satellite
from low earth orbit around 300 or so
kilometers above the surface of the
planet
now why does the u.s want a ban or a
moratorium
because firstly they have essentially
perfected the technology they don't have
any more testing to do just like the
nuclear weapons ban
so there is this uh ctbd right the
comprehensive test ban treaty nuclear
weapons testing the americans did
hundreds maybe thousands of tests in the
20th century and when they had all the
data they needed and then they had
perfected their weapons design that's
when they imposed the ban and various
countries signed it
and india missed the bus we could have
also tested nuclear weapons in the 1970s
and all that but
we decided not to
and when we did test in 1998 there was
this entire
slew of sanctions imposed upon india
and this time india has been smart we
tested an asap weapon before any such
talk of a ban
happened and that's why we are now in
the big club the club of four the four
nations that have anti-satellite missile
technology
so the u.s wants a ban because they
don't no longer need to do any more
tests so once you have done all your
tests you impose a ban and then you
prevent other nations
from testing the technology
very smart isn't it
and there's another reason as well
one of the ways of killing a satellite
is through a kinetic kill weapon like an
anti-satellite missile but there are
other ways of killing satellites you
could kill a satellite with lasers
you can kill a satellite using laser
weapons if you have a powerful enough
laser which can be targeted
aimed accurately at a satellite
so the americans have been testing laser
weapons for quite some time
and yeah so they may have now by now
the technology to destroy a satellite
using a laser a laser is essentially a
very concentrated beam of light
so that's one thing the other way of
destroying or disabling a satellite is
by hacking it
cyber warfare
so you could
essentially take over a satellite hijack
a satellite and make it do weird stuff
what it's not designed to do just by
hacking it taking it taking it over
using cyber warfare
you could disable it you could destroy
its
its chip its chip architecture or
whatever or you could make it you can
take it over and use it against the
parent country
if you have the cyber
warfare capabilities to do that
and such things have happened
in recent times
such things have happened a spacecraft
have been
hijacked and made to do things that they
were not supposed to do and such things
have happened i will not give you
examples
but it's possible it has happened the us
has the ability to do that
the russians for sure have the ability
the chinese also have the ability
to hack and hijack a satellite so when
you have laser weapons when you can take
over a satellite and disable it
electronically through cyber means then
why do you need asap weapons
so now that these new technologies have
emerged asap weapons don't make a lot of
sense
so the us wants to impose a ban or a
moratorium on asat testing
and of course they will want to
impose that on the rest of the world
so that it so that other countries
cannot acquire the technology by means
of testing it
so that's how it is so it will not hurt
their national interest they've moved on
to other forms of technology and they're
just fine
and they will ban those forms of
technology only after they perfected
that that also so that's how it goes
next question by marcus
marcus
the question is why do so many people
from the indian subcontinent live in
cyprus hmm
does this have something to do with
anything to do with the political
situation and the division of the island
in 1974 after the war what is india's
relationship like with each side greek
and turkish thank you so much okay
this is an interesting question do you
guys ladies gents all know where cyprus
is
so you know what's coming i'm gonna
share my screen and show you the map
okay where is the island of cyprus
it is definitely not in the indian ocean
region
cyprus is
in the mediterranean
so as you know this here is india you
know where india is let's go westwards
further west
further west and this here now
is the mediterranean sea and this island
here
is the island of cyprus now historically
this has been greek territory but today
it is divided
into
it is the island is essentially
partitioned today if you can see on the
map there is a no man's land
the northern part of cyprus is now
under turkish occupation
and the south part of cyprus is under
greek control
originally it was entirely under control
in 1974 or whatever the date is the
turks invaded and took over
uh the northern part of the island so
the capital city nicosia itself is a
city that's divided into two the turkish
portion and the greek portion so that is
the story of cyprus that's the situation
that we have today uh it lies to the
south of turkey in the mediterranean sea
and to the west of syria and lebanon
so that's where cyprus is today i hope
that that explains where cyprus is
geographically
now let's come back to the question if
the question is why do many people
from the indian subcontinent especially
india
why do so many people of from this
region live in cyprus many of them have
the citizenship of cyprus
well i'll tell you one i'll give you a
clue
they all have they're all millionaires
they all have a few million dollars to
burn
or invest so to say so there is
something called
citizenship by investment
which means that you can you have to
invest a certain amount of money in in a
certain country
and they will offer you citizenship in
exchange
so uh so countries countries like cyprus
have this
system this program
uh i believe jamaica also has it a
couple of countries in the caribbean
region
offer this whether it's the whether it's
jamaica or some other country
in the caribbean but there is certainly
at least one country that i kind of
remember in the caribbean that offers
citizenship by investment
the australians offer you
something similar even the new
zealanders offering something similar
something similar exists in spain
in portugal as well
in the u.s you have something called a
golden visa which means that if you
invest i think
how much is it one million dollars in a
us business then you get a green card
and our various such programs in various
parts of the world
essentially
what it means is that you can buy
a green card or a citizenship a green
card is one step close one step away
from citizenship
in cyprus you can i think obtain
citizenship right away or within
three to six months if you invest a
certain amount of money in the country
and i'm not sure what the amount of
money is you can look it up google it i
think it will be
in excess of a million dollars if i'm
not mistaken if i remember correctly
and you also have to buy some property
you to buy a very expensive house and
invest some money in cyprus if you do
that within a few months you get a
passport and then you can choose to give
up your indian passport or just quietly
retained no if no one knows many people
actually illegally retain two passports
in india the law is such that if you
obtain the citizenship of another
country then you have to give up your
you have to
surrender your indian passport
immediately which means you can not have
dual citizenship if you're an indian but
there are certain people are not naming
anybody in names but there are some
people who quietly retain the indian
passport as well
so
the answer is very simple
cyprus offers
a citizenship by investment and that's
why there are so many people from india
many people from india who
live there and who have a cypress
passport and what's the what is the
benefit of having a passport from cyprus
well the benefit is that cyprus is part
of the european union
if you have a cyprus passport
cypriot passport then you can move to
any part
of the eu the european union and you
don't need a visa to go there which
essentially opens up much of western
europe to you just that passport you
don't need a visa to go there
so it it offers you greater mobility and
and such other benefits and advantages
and that's why lots of people
opt
to
essentially purchase
a passport of from cyprus
if you have enough money so that's the
answer and that's why lots of indians
live there and have citizenship there
what's india's relationship like like
with each side greek and turkish
india's relationship with turkey is
well
it's okay
not the friendliest of relationships the
turks as we know they support pakistan
in most matters which is
automatically going to guarantee that
india and turkey don't have a very good
relationship when it comes to india and
greece
i'm not sure what the relationship is
like i mean historically if you go back
three thousand years then india and
greece had very strong
close ties
from the perspective of trade and
culture and history and whatnot but
as of today i'm not sure what the
relationship is like greece is not a
very important country it's not a very
big
major country in europe
it is not a very strong or powerful
country either economically or
geopolitically or militarily
so it's not very high on india's radar
when it comes to geopolitics but i am
sure india and greece have a warm
friendly and cordial relationship no
major issues as such
so that is what i can tell you
okay next question is by shaman tawar
the question is india is referred to as
a developing country when is a country
fully developed what is the role of
indian culture languages and values in
the development of the country thank you
in advance okay good question
there is no clear definition of what is
a developing country and a developed
country one of the ways of looking at it
as is that
developing countries are low-income
countries
fully developed countries or
industrialized countries are high-income
countries
and there is something in between which
is the middle income nations
so when you talk about a low income
nation it's typically an income less
than five thousand dollars per capita
5000 us dollars per capita right now
india's per capita gdp will be somewhere
around two thousand dollars per capita
which is which is low income
so that's why india is a low income
country or a developing country china is
now a middle income country its gdp per
capita is around ten thousand dollars
so it's not quite an industrialized
nation but it's a rapidly
industrializing nation
and then you have nations like the u.s
the uk western europe and all which have
very high gdp per capita numbers
maybe two
upwards of twenty thousand dollars per
per capita maybe thirty forty fifty
thousand dollars per capita depending on
which nation it is australia i would
imagine would have a gdp per capita of
more than fifty thousand dollars
so those are the fully developed fully
industrialized nations
so that's also the distinction between
the first world the second world and the
third world the second world is
essentially the middle income nations
and the third world is low income nation
so by the definition india is still
currently part of the third world once
india reaches uh
india's
gdp reaches the 15 trillion dollar mark
that's when india will become more or
less a middle-income nation
give it another 20 years we should be
there if things go well
so that's when india is no longer a
developing country but a near developed
country or so so something like that
so that is roughly how it is the
difference between a developing country
a fully developed country and a rapidly
developing or so country right
what's the role of indian culture
languages and values in the development
of the country none whatsoever
when we're talking about the development
of a country we're talking about
material development
there are certain nations that have that
don't have the greatest
or the most
advanced culture
i'm talking about historically
let's not
i'm not naming any specific country but
historically let's talk about rome
the roman empire rome was never a
civilization rome was always an empire
and they borrowed culture from the
greeks and other places their culture
was never the greatest
and yet they were the most
advanced widespread
and
developed
uh
empire of that time in europe
right
so it's all about material development
it's all about the size of your economy
gdp per capita overall gdp your military
strength that is what we take into
consideration when we talk about
development
you may have the most advanced culture
in the world but if your country is a
low-income country no one's gonna
respect you and no one's gonna consider
you to be a developed country so there
is no i mean
see let's not get it wrong
culture languages values all that is
very important from us from a cultural
perspective
from a long term for from a long-term
civilizational perspective we cannot
neglect that
but when it comes to our global standing
economic standing and geopolitical
standing it's all about material
development it's all about hard power
it's all about hard power so let's stop
obsessing about soft power for some time
until we reach the 15 trillion dollar
mark and then we'll talk
all right so that is
the only thing that matters in
your global
standing economically military
militarily and geopolitically
if you're talking about global respect
they'll respect you only if you're
strong from an economic and military
perspective
your culture doesn't matter these days
if you'll notice if you travel
internationally you will notice that
there is a little more respect that you
get if you're indian
people
there is a
people have a better opinion of india
these days
it's because india is now developing
rapidly india is standing up for itself
economically militarily and
geopolitically
india is showing spine for the first
time in 70 years
that's why
indians who travel abroad get a little
more respect than these two
than they used to get 20 years ago
so it's all about material progress and
material development that's all it is
asmitha says why is there no minimum
educational qualification required to
become a politician in india is it is it
possible and practical to have a formal
education system and a degree mandatory
for people who want to become
politicians
where the curriculum includes topics
like geopolitics history microeconomics
and so on
also why does the constitution consider
voting as a right is it why is it not a
duty yeah all right good question
i think it is a
well
it's it's a
very good question it's a good sentiment
but i don't think it's practical because
if it were practical
some country in the world would have
implemented something like this
even if you look at the us
if you look at western europe if you
look at all the developed nations
australia new zealand whatever france
or any other country in the world none
of these nations
has such a requirement of some kind of
educational qualification which is a
prerequisite for um
standing for public office or becoming a
politician
so it's not political it's not
feasible simply because
everybody has the right to vote in a
democracy and similarly everybody has
the right to stand for election
uh ideally that would be great i think
it it makes sense for
people who want to stand for leadership
positions
to actually have some kind of background
in these
matters
we need some
reasonable understanding of science
especially physics
also economics history geopolitics
what is power what is the national
interest you would need
it would be great if politicians had a
good background and a solid
understanding of that
but it is not feasible because
of various factors first of all let's
take india itself our education system
is terrible
even if you were to offer a degree in
way in something like this like
leadership
what is the guarantee that that degree
is going to is going to mean something
is going to actually make a person
understand things in india in the indian
education system if you want to pass a
degree if you want to acquire a degree
you only have to pass an exam you have
to memorize stuff and then write long
essays in a three-hour exam
and if you perform that ritual properly
you get the degree
it doesn't mean that you have actually
learned anything
lots of people acquire degrees without
actually understanding any subject our
education system is so terrible and so
are many other education systems around
the world i mean today the u.s education
system is going backwards
it's become a joke it's increasingly
becoming more and more of a joke
i mean just look at what the professors
have to say
look at what i mean
just a couple of examples jordan
peterson gad sad
the peterson is from canada gaza is also
from canada i believe but there are
plenty of people from the u.s as well
and just see what they have to say about
their own education system in north
america
it's going from bad to us so when you
have a broken education system
then
having a degree doesn't mean that the
kids like the
degree holder will actually have some
knowledge about this stuff so it's like
that so there are a variety of reasons
why it has never been implemented
historically and even today
and
it's always possible that a person who
doesn't hold a degree may actually be
way better educated than a person who
has
acquired a degree you see cases like
that all the time
talk about freeman dyson one of the
greatest physicists of all time
he said the
the
inventor or the person who put forth the
dyson sphere
one of the visionary physicists of the
20th century
he did not have a phd and he's one of
the greats so there are lots of examples
like that so uh a degree doesn't
guarantee anything
and even studying a subject doesn't
guarantee anything the person will
actually learn anything so there's a
variety of factors why this has never
been practically feasible
uh why does the constitution consider
voting as a right why not a duty well
ask the people who framed the
constitution
they blindly copied a patchwork of
western constitutions one piece from
here one piece from there and put it all
together in a weird patchwork and that's
what the indian constitution is
uh maybe it should be a duty
so yeah
i've said this multiple times that we
need to revisit our constitution when
the time is right we need a new
constitution a better constitution a
constitution that is grounded and rooted
in indian civilizational values
and which puts
the indian national interest front and
center right now the constitution does
not do that so yeah it needs to happen
eventually when the time is right maybe
the time is not right right now perhaps
okay um
what's the solution against regular mass
shootings in the us
the u.s second amendment gives citizens
rights to acquire and bear guns because
they had fought for the nation's
independence however the mass shootings
are happening regularly for years and
nothing substantial is being done
you are right nothing substantial is
being done and
funnily enough
i mean tragically actually there's only
one nation one country where this
happens on a regular basis is the us and
yet the politicians there
claim that nothing can be done about
this
if you are the only country where this
sort of thing happens on a routine basis
then why can't something be done the
mothers just learn from the other
nations which where this doesn't happen
what are they doing with what that
you're not doing
take india this never happens in india
and one of the reasons is because it's
very very very hard to obtain a gun
license you can't have a personal a
firearm without having a license
and it's
next to impossible to obtain a gun
license in the u.s
you can walk into a grocery store or a
supermarket and buy
a gun
and various kinds of rifles
various kinds of semi-automatic weapons
and various kinds of bump stocks etc
that can transform your semi-automatic
weapon into a fully automatic machine
gun
there was this uh
terrible tragedy in las vegas
two or three years ago
more than 50 people lost their lives and
more than 2 300 people were injured
there was a
gunman firing
at a
crowd in a concert from a hotel
with automatic weapons i mean he was
using a bump stock that that transformed
a
semi-automatic rifle into an automatic
rifle and this thing happens all the
time it's because it's so easy to
acquire
guns in the us there are more guns than
people in in this country
right and
society
in the u.s has become such that people
don't trust each other people are scared
of each other
and so you have these tragedies
happening on a almost daily basis
since
i had read this weird statistic
somewhere
since 1950 or 1960 or whatever
more americans have died in domestic gun
violence
than
the number of soldiers american soldiers
that died since 19
that died since the american war of
independence
so that's what's happening in the nation
it's a nation that's
gone crazy
then we know they know what needs to be
done all they have to do is to ban guns
but they have the second amendment
amendment which gives the
citizens the right to bear arms
and there is this very powerful gun
lobby firearms lobby which which makes
billions of dollars selling guns and
they want to protect that source of
revenue
so
it's always
capitalism or the
interest of the people it's always
commercial interests over the interests
of the people that's what u.s society is
terrible terrible terrible terrible what
can i say
and that's why this is something that
keeps going on and on it keeps happening
every week nowadays it's just terrible
and sad to see that
what's happening i mean in schools
kids
terrible
so
we all know what the politicians need to
do but
they won't do it
why is that well
because politicians
have interests
various kinds of interests maybe they
are hand in glove with various
industries
and that's how it goes
so that's why this
thing keeps on happening
okay they just says why did india return
the georgian queen's relics in 2021
what's the history and significance of
this
so if you want the exact details i would
recommend that you watch my podcast with
dr niraj dry in which there is a segment
in which we discussed this and it was dr
niles
and his team that had worked on this
case
so i don't remember what the dates are
and all that but there was this queen
from georgia
who was held hostage by
which
by one of the
kings in a neighboring country from not
sure whether it's azerbaijan or some
turkic nation
turkic kingdom she was held hostage
for
i think over a decade
and eventually she was murdered on the
orders of the king
and uh
murdered in a terrible way
now
her
relics her body
she was christian and this queen was a
muslim king or whatever that's how the
story goes so after she was murdered her
body was transported by her followers
to india i believe it was to goa or some
such place
and it was buried there apparently
right
and this matter is like more than two
three hundred years old if i'm not
mistaken you can look up the exact dates
the name is queen ketevan k-e-t-e-v-a-n
look it up google it and you'll find the
exact details i'm giving you the broad
picture
now
um so recently some bones were found in
this this place
and uh
i believe there was a request from the
georgian government to the indian
government to investigate this case if
possible
uh locate
the relics of the queen
and see if a positive identification is
possible
so a number of bones were found and dr
niraja and his team they did genetic
analysis of these bones
and they were able to identify
a set of bones
in which you had a haplogroup or a
lineage a genetic lineage that is found
in georgia not india
and that means that it is
most likely that that
those bones belong to that queen because
we know that that queen's body and her
bones were transported to india and
buried in this location
and that's how they were able to
identify the dead queen's
bones her relics after such a long time
and then
the indian government repatriated
those relics to the home country of
queen
which is georgia
it's a it's a good deed that we did
after all these years after centuries we
sent her body back to her homeland where
she can be buried and put to rest
honorably
so it's a good thing we did and that is
that is
why we did that just to do a good deed
and to
strengthen our relations with this
nation georgia
so that in very brief is the story if
you want a
more detailed explanation look up my
podcast on this channel the podcast the
conversation that i had with dr nirajai
and i'm sure there's plenty of material
available online as well you can google
it
queen ketevan
all right
okay this is by akash the what's the
term martial races mean
i'm just aware of the fact that the
british preferred and enlisted most of
the military personnel from these
so-called races which included rajputs
jaats gurjars etc does it make any sense
historically and scientifically as you
once said that races don't mean anything
scientifically speaking
so the term the british used is martial
races m-a-r-t-i-a-l
marshall which means the
like like the term that we use martial
arts
m-a-r-t-i-a-l marshall which means uh
military kind of military which is
something to do with something to do
with warfare
so the martial races it's a term that
the british
coined
was used to designate certain ethnic
supposed ethnic groups in india
one of these was the rajputs one of
these was the six and the jaat and the
gurjars i believe that
the pashtuns may have been included in
this
and also the gorkhas
if i am not mistaken
so a number of these so called races
or ethnicities
were designated by the british as
martial races and this was i believe
part of the old policy good old policy
of divide and conquer you give certain
people or certain strata of society
certain extra privileges you make them
feel like you are they are superior in
some way
and that buys you their loyalty
so that's the kind of thing they did
it was part of the policy of divide and
rule the british were past masters at
that
so they designated certain
ethnicities or certain people certain
certain indian groups ethnic groups as
martial races and what they would do is
that they would
hire from these so-called martial races
exclusively almost exclusively into the
british indian army
so that's why they created these various
regiments named after various
so-called martial races the rajput
regiment rajputana rifles and sikh
regiment
chart regiment gore couragement and so
on so forth
so that was the strategy the policy that
they used and it's something we are
still continuing today
we still have the same
colonial names given to various
regiments
which is not the right thing in our
opinion
uh anyhow so that is the policy the
british
used now scientifically we all know i
mean
races
are not really a scientific thing
scientifically there is no real concept
of race a pure race that's
scientifically it's nonsense
if you look at genetic studies there is
no
delineation between race x and race y
even in india there is this talk for the
past 200 years of the dravidian race in
the aryan race where genetically we are
all the same we are very much the same
and therefore the entire concept of race
has no basis in science it's
unscientific it's pseudoscientific it is
a pseudoscience scientific and racist
concept
so it makes no sense historically and
scientifically
okay divya rabari says you've spoken
about keeping the group you trust large
and the people you needed to keep in
power and to keep you in power small
can you share some more laws on power
okay
so uh yeah it's about the laws of power
right the hidden laws of power power
trumps money and how you come to power
how you
remain in power and so on how you expand
your power base and all that stuff so
one of the rules of power is that
you keep the group
that you trust or the group of people
that is loyal to you
as large as possible
and the second law is that you keep the
group of people
you rely on the indispensable people you
keep that group as small as possible
right that's two things
the third law let me add one more law in
there
is that you use money to buy loyalty
so that this group that you want to make
as large as possible that can be bought
with money
right
i mean if you look at the policy of any
dictator you will see that happening
again using that
that being carried out again and again
whether it's saddam hussein whether it
is kim jong-un whether it's the chinese
communist party or any other
dictatorship that you have seen in in
history
these are the laws these are the rules
they follow
keep the group of people you who that
are indispensable to you
keep that group as small as possible
keep the people who are loyal to you
that group as large as possible and use
money to buy more loyalty
so as you become powerful you can use
money as fuel to buy more power
but if you have a lot of money but no
power you can't do anything with that
so uh
that's how power works it's like
it's like a corporation you have a big
company let's say you have a fortune 500
company and you are the person who is
the biggest largest shareholder
you have a group of people who work for
you the ceo the ceo the cfo etc there
are there are there's a small group of
people who are indispensable to the
running of the company you keep that
group as small as possible
and then
you hire employees with the money that
you have and make that group as large as
you need it to be but not larger than
that
so that's how it goes these are the some
of the rules of power
there's much more to that but i'm just
giving a brief
cursory overview
okay amazing indian citizen says what
are your views on hyperloop
transportation is it group is it good
for mass transportation should india
adopt it on a large scale
so what is the hyperloop the hyperloop
is something that elon musk is building
is is a
is working on he has a company called
the boring company i think
which is working on the hyperloop
technology i think richard branson's
virgin group is also working on
hyperloop technology and so on
so what is hyperloop technology
you have a a tube below the surface of
the earth
in which you have a train
that is most likely levitated either
magnetically or on a cushion of air and
this tunnel is mostly evacuated which
means that it is mostly devoid of air
and if you evacuate the tunnel make it
more or less like a vacuum then there is
no air resistance which means that there
is no upper limit on the speed at which
your train can travel
right so that is in brief in a nutshell
what the hyperloop transportation is
is it good for mass transportation well
it depends
the human see human beings have a
certain tolerance a certain limit of the
tolerance to
to being shaken around
so you may have noticed this if you're
traveling by air on a plane and there is
turbulence
we know that planes travel at 500 600
700 800 kilometers per hour depending on
where you are
that speed if there is turbulence then
you are shaken up or down or side by
side and if that continues for too long
you're gonna have nausea you're gonna
end up vomiting and the same thing
happens when you're traveling by car if
there is too much movement if the driver
is not good and he or she keeps moving
the car around too fast and too rapidly
from side to side then you're going to
develop nausea that happens in cars and
buses and planes in ships
when you go on ships you get the sea
sickness because of this constant
movement that you're not used to that
causes nausea
and i think the limit of the human
tolerance tolerance to nausea to this
kind of phenomenon
is too
not sure what it is there is a certain
radius of curvature beyond which if you
go you're gonna develop nausea now in
the case of and that is that depends on
the speed the higher the speed at which
you're traveling the
the
greater should be the radius of
curvature otherwise you will develop
nausea or you'll you will get intensely
sick
you may even lose consciousness if it
goes beyond the point
when it comes to the hyperloop we're
talking about traveling at
nearly the speed of an aircraft
maybe 700 800 900 kilometers per hour
possibly possibly at such high speeds
if you have any
uh
curvature of your path
there is a higher chance of the
breaching the limit
of of the tolerance to nausea
and we know that the earth is curved
we are on a
roughly
round planet
and the curvature of the earth itself
could impose a limitation
uh on the speed at which you can travel
unless you can drill a straight line
extremely straight uh paths
below the surface of the earth and and
cut out the curvature of the earth as
well so there are all these problems
if you look at the high speed trains
that you have anywhere in the world
whether it's in japan whether it's the
uh trains in france or tgv trains over
there it's in china
there is a limit beyond which the the
speed limit beyond which they don't go
especially when they are going on a
curved path when they're turbine turn
turning
so all that has to be taken into account
and because of that
there may be limits to the speed at
which hyperloop can transport human
beings
and those limits may be such that it may
not be very financially viable to create
these hyperloop
systems
you can just
have
above the surface trains
so hyperloop is still something that is
being studied
being researched
it may or may not be great
for high-speed transportation for human
beings it will be certainly great for
cargo for transporting cargo
so it's something that needs to be
validated and
tested further
so i believe india should not start
investing in the hyperloop technology
until it is proven in other countries
then we can acquire it
okay abhinav says please speak about
ancient india which is said to be filled
with scientific marvels and mysteries
well india had this reputation in
ancient times of being this
scientifically most and technologically
most advanced civilization in the world
everybody
knew that about india i'm talking about
the neighbors china the romans the
greeks the arabs the persians and so on
so and so forth india was always the
most technologically advanced
civilization until the last 1000 years
right
now
let's let's take an example
there is this uh collection of stories
in arabic
called the arabian nights i believe
the arabian nights
it's a collection of stories most of
these stories are inspired by the
panchatantra and the jataka tales
now there is one story one of these
stories is what is it called the ebony
horse or something
in which
there is this
indian engineer or
indian guy
who comes to a city in iran i think it
was shiraz in iran
and he comes on a
mechanical
flying horse
and there's a whole story around that
around this flying horse so an indian
person an indian engineer
had built a horse a mechanical horse
that could actually fly in there it
could fly to great heights
so that's the kind of reputation india
had
of having the most advanced technology
in the world so that's just one example
there are lots of other examples so
that's the kind of
past that india had i am not sure if we
had flying horses in vimanas and all
that but at least our neighbors
seemed to believe that right
okay this is a question by baka nami
makanani
i'm currently reading mandala one of an
english translation of the rigveda
i have come to know that somaras was a
juice extracted
by stones crushing a plant
it's not mentioned anywhere that it was
an alcoholic drink
can you tell me what was sumarus some
say it was wine but wine is made from
grapes one from a plant
please answer this question
okay
listen if i have the answer i'll
i'll have an answer that nobody else has
been able to find
in the past
several centuries
see as of today nobody knows
what somaras actually was
what we know is that there was a plant
whose stalks were crushed between stones
or through some some press the juice was
extracted and it was the greatest drink
of the vedic age it was not an
intoxicating drink it was not an
alcoholic drink but it was something
that invigorated you and gave you
energy gave you bravery it is something
you drank before you went into battle
so it had
certain qualities like that
one could call it
reasonably
accurately to be a performance enhancing
drink of some kind today you have red
bull and monster energy and and what not
so apparently somaras
was the holy the sacred
performance in enhancing drink of the
vedic age
so clearly so there have been
a number of theories
one of the theories is that it was a
silo cyber mushroom but the texts don't
mention any mushroom they mention a
plant with long
stalks
s-t-a-l-k-s stalks
so it's a plant whose stalks were
crushed to extract the juice which was
drunk and it gave you great powers great
energy
so one of the theories like i say like i
said was the silo cyber mushroom that
seems to be a theory that should not be
taken that seriously
uh another theory says that it is the
ephedra plant
which grows in mountainous regions
it grows in the himalayas
in kashmir
and in many parts of central asia
so there is something that they have
used to push the aryan invasion myth the
or the migration myth that the aryans
the vedic aryans they lived in central
asia where this plant was available and
after they reached india they lost all
um
access to this plant and that's why soma
has become a big mystery we don't quite
know what it is
the ephedra plant does grow
in the himalayas in parts of india in
kashmir and so on so forth so it's not
something that's beyond india as such
so the the truth is that we don't quite
know yet
we don't quite know we don't have a
conclusive answer as to what the soma
plant was
we know it was not alcoholic
we know that it was not alcohol we know
that it was not intoxicating
but it was invigorating
so it's something that our great
wonderful historians have not really
looked into
european scholars have tried to
speculate about this but there is no
clear answer as of today so
unfortunately i will not be able to
answer your question i can give you the
various prevailing
hypotheses but none of these have been
proven yet
shogun khan says do mongols use
crossbows
i
suppose you are trying to ask me whether
the mongols used crossbows in the past
today
no one uses crossbows
so uh
historically the mongols used a
composite
bow
it was a double curved bow
similar to the bow that these kittens
and ancient indians used
uh
it was made up of
wood and bone and sinew and various
other things it was a very strong bow
and
typically mongolian archers would have
lopsided shoulders one shoulder would be
over developed because of the amount of
energy they need to put they needed to
put in their practice and their fingers
would get really really hard
because those were really
hard bows to to
you know use
so historically the traditional mongol
and bow was the double curved
composite bow
but
during the times of the great lord shri
khingis khan the mongolians conquered
china twice
and the thing about the mongols was that
they were always happy
to acquire and
absorb new technology
and the chinese used crossbars
uh from the
uh the chinese have a history in the
past two two and a half thousand years
of using crossbows so the mongols came
across crossbows when they invaded china
they came across the
armored clothing as well
so these are things they borrowed from
the chinese
and from that point forwards
uh mongolian
soldiers would use the composite bow as
well as the crossbar
so to make a long answer short yes the
mongols did eventually end up using
crossbars during their conquests
abhishek says can you please explain the
power trump's wealth
thing with an example other than that of
sri chang is khan there are hundreds of
examples you can think of
let's
think of something more recent in 2016
donald j trump became the president of
the us
he was very clear about the things that
he wanted to achieve he wanted to build
a big wall between the u.s and mexico he
wanted a certain kind of foreign policy
what was he able to achieve
he was the president of the us for four
years
was he able to build the wall
no
was he able to
have the kind of foreign policy that we
wanted
no
he was a he is a very wealthy man
but as the president of the u.s he was
in office but not really in power
if he was truly
in power he would have built that wall
he would have implemented various
aspects of his foreign policy
and so on
when he went to europe to meet with
various
world leaders from nato
from the eu
he found that he was not even
treated with appropriate respect
because he was never really in power he
was only in office
he did not he was not a part of the us
political establishment he was an
outsider
he managed
to win the election
but he was stymied at every step of the
way
his own party voted against him during
the impeachment proceedings that's why
they were the the they were able to
impeach him
that is an excellent example of power
trump's wealth this man was one of the
wealthiest people in the us and yet
even as the president of the u.s he was
powerless
he could achieve nothing
power always trumps wealth he was never
in power they always saw him as an
outsider and they did not allow him to
do anything that he wanted to do as the
president of the u.s let's take another
example
closer to home
one of the richest persons in china
is jack
ma
he is one of the richest persons in the
world
should that not mean that he should be
more powerful than
most members of the chinese communist
party
should that not mean
that he should be more powerful than xi
jinping
and yet he is not
yet he is not he disappeared for a few
months after he fell foul
of the chinese communist party
he disappeared for a few months he
eventually reappeared with a long
profusely apologetic video apologizing
for all the various financial and other
misleads he had done
essentially
a person as wealthy as jack ma
has less power
than a random chinese communist party
district official
you understand that so wealth
is nothing unless you have real power
wealth is meaningless without power yeah
sure you will live a reasonably
comfortable life but you will never be
able to achieve the things that a
politician can achieve even low-level
politicians achieve
so that's how it is you may be one of
the richest people in whatever country
you're living in but a local district
official
can be more powerful than you are and
can get more things done than what what
you can do so power always trumps wealth
i've given two examples there are lots
more that you can think of
if you can see it
okay let's take a couple more questions
then we will go somewhere else uh aman
says we know that longitudes on the
earth demark time and all the
longitudinal lines meet at the poles so
what is the time at the poles time is
meaningless at the poles typically what
you do when you are at the near the
north pole
or in antarctica what you do is
you use the time of your country
so if you're an indian scientist in
antarctica near the south pole
then you will use ist indian standard
time
if you are an argentinian scientist or
or whatever near in in antarctica you
will use the argentinian time and so on
and so forth so time has no real meaning
at the polls but you can use whatever
time you choose
over there typically you will choose at
local time of your own country that's
how it is
all right next question is by dhruvit
joshi
i was never never able to understand the
concept of heat what is heat
fundamentally is it a form of energy is
it just the vibration of molecules or
does it cause the vibration of molecules
please help us understand see
it's very simple
heat is a form of energy
every
see all quantities in physics
have a certain
unit
time has the unit of second length is
the unit of meter mass kilograms
electric current amperes temperature
kelvin
and so on and so forth these are the
units so what is the unit
of
heat the unit of heat is very simple it
is the joule the joule is a derived unit
kilogram meter squared per second
squared that is the unit of energy so
it's very simple the unit of heat
is the joule and therefore heat is
nothing but a form of energy you take a
rod of metal iron rod
and you heat it up it means it has more
energy now that heat that energy came
from somewhere else
you had to impart that energy into that
iron rod to make it glow
so
to to keep it very simple heat is
nothing but a form of energy that's all
it is it does not
it it is not the vibration of molecules
it is what causes
the vibration of molecules all right
sanatorium says why does society favor
extroverts
well
see society is the
the interaction of human beings
the cliche says says that man
is a social animal
humans are social animals and society is
made up of the is built out of the
interaction and cooperation and
coordination of various human beings
so the more
amenable
you are to
interacting with other human beings the
more an integral part of society you can
be
so those who are extroverts are
naturally more inclined to
interacting more frequently and more
strongly with other people and that's
why they
society
naturally gives them a more favorable
role
in society
introverts are people who kind of keep
to themselves don't talk a lot and so on
so that's why
typically
they would have
a lesser role to play in society which
is not always the case
historically
most great scientists and most great uh
entrepreneurs industrialists etc
not most but significant
proportion of these have been introverts
i would say in the case of scientists
most great scientists must have been
introverts
even when it comes to uh
billionaires etc
think about somebody like elon musk he
is not quite an extrovert right and and
there must be lots of other examples
so um it's not always the case
especially when you reach the higher
levels of society with the top one
percent or the top one percent of the
one percent over there it's actually it
may be the case that introverts are more
represented than extroverts
but overall
when it comes to the average human being
i think extroverts stand a higher have
typically a higher position or role
in society just because of the way they
are built
they are better at small talk
introverts don't know what small talk is
extroverts can just go and talk to just
anybody and talk about any topic small
talk how's the weather how are you doing
blah blah blah which introverts don't
quite understand so that's the advantage
that extroverts have
but
in the long run maybe not quite the case
so
that's where that's how it is
uh let's take a couple of questions more
shweda says is it really sensible for a
40 year old someone to be running behind
career ignoring their own health
not sleeping well tight diet not giving
the mind a rest what do you think will
be the repercussions is the body a
machine the body is not a machine
in
modern medicine the body is considered
to be a system
with different organs a collection of
organs like india is supposedly a
collection of states somebody said
recently
look
it's more than that
the body affects the mind the mind
affects the body if you're unhappy the
body becomes ill
or if you are ill the body the mind
becomes unhappy and so on so forth it's
not quite a machine it's something
beyond that
and this is this is something that
applies to everybody not only somebody
in their 40s even somebody in their
teens if they don't take care of the
health it's going to affect
everything
so it is good to be ambitious you have
to be ambitious if you want to get ahead
in life
but one does need to take care of these
things especially sleep sleep is a
superpower you sleep the average human
being needs eight hours of sleep you
sleep eight hours properly in a dark
room
and uninterrupted sleep it's gonna give
you so much energy and power that or
other people won't get
so one needs to take care of sleeping
properly eating the right kind of food
not eating garbage
and exercising regularly if you do that
you're going to do well in life in the
long term
that applies to people in any stage of
life teenagers 20 years old people and
even people in their 40s and beyond
all right one more question
suraj says amber heard of johnny depp or
johnny depp obviously johnny depp
obviously
okay let me take a few questions from
the live chat
from the live chat what do we have
you have any questions for me ask them
now and i will take a few more
someone says sleep is more important
than food well if you don't eat food
[Laughter]
well sleep won't matter a lot
it's all important all of these things
are important you just need to have a
certain kind of balance the right kind
of balance it depends from person to
person everybody is built differently
everybody has a different kind of
genetics different metabolism different
amount of sleep you need and so on so
forth you have to understand who you are
what your body is like what your mind is
like and do what is best for you so you
first learn to listen to your body in
your mind
that takes time
okay
what else do we have uh some questions
abhishek says what do you think of india
as a future superpower yes i think india
is a future superpower if we get things
right it will be
a superpower by 2050 for sure if we get
things right if with the right
leadership we will do it
okay
um
saurabh says why is russia unable to
defeat ukraine completely when they have
more and more arms and ammunition
to answer this question we have to
understand what russia's true motives
are or were
do we know what was the objective of the
invasion
did mr putin put out a tweet saying that
okay this is my objective within the
next these many days i want to conquer
the whole of ukraine did he say that did
he make an announcement like that
so why are we assuming
that the objective of this military
operation was to take over the whole of
ukraine
why are we assuming this
did it did mr putin say that that was
his objective
we don't know what the true objectives
were
perhaps the objective was to only take
over eastern ukraine and the black sea
coast
maybe that was the objective
maybe they don't don't want to take over
the whole of ukraine maybe they want to
take over only the russian-speaking
popul
portions of ukraine
which they more or less have taken they
have already taken out the russians have
already conquered
one-fourth of ukraine
they have conquered a territory that is
larger than the area of bangladesh or
nepal
right
and they have done that without using
much of the air force and much of the
army
they have
this enormous aerial firepower they have
a huge air force that they have not used
they have arms ammunition missiles they
have everything
they chose not to use that maybe they
only wanted to capture what they have
captured and maybe a little bit more and
i believe that whenever mr putin decides
that he has achieved his objectives
he will declare a ceasefire
unilaterally
and then we are done
so
a country has captured
a territory that is greater larger than
the territory of nepal or bangladesh
i don't i think that's a huge
achievement maybe that is what they were
after we don't know what they were after
so that is where we are let's not assume
things that the objective was to capture
the entire area that we see on the map
maybe not
only time will tell us what the real
objectives were
okay what else do we have
have you read carl sagan's demon haunted
world
what's your perspective
i haven't read it i've heard about it
the demon haunted world
not sure what it's about maybe i will
read it in the future if i do ever get
the time
is a global nato possible will india
become a member of this group if you
have a global nato
it means that every country is a part of
that
right a global nato means a
nato that incorporates the whole globe
which means that every country is part
of it
if it is a global group then india will
obviously be a part of this group
but why would somebody create a global
nato
i don't see such a thing ever happening
personally
all right
rishi says
is geopolitics raj dharma
creating instability in other nations
for oil in your country your people what
u.s did
geopolitics is about serving your nation
it's about furthering your national
interest that is what raj dharma is
your duty is your nation your kingdom
your empire
and your people
that is the
only duty that you have
their long-term national interest in
their long-term prosperity that's all
your duty is you don't have a duty to
the citizens of other countries
and to other nations
and other nations are going to try and
exploit your nation so it is your duty
to go ahead and exploit their nations
that's how it works in geopolitics these
are the lessons that our great lord
vishnu gupta chanakya
gave to us
and that's the rules that we have to
play by that's how it goes
right what else do we have
was the american war of independence
actually britishers versus britishers
british versus british yes it was
that's what it was see it's like this
the british
a bunch of european nations colonized
the americas the spaniards
colonized south america to some extent
the portuguese as well
and it was the
british and the french mostly who
colonized
north america the entire continent
now
after some time the british who were in
north america
were able to secure their own territory
defeat the french push the french up
north it eventually became canada
then
they they asked themselves why should we
continue paying taxes
to the british
empire to the british crown
why can't we just take this land over
for ourselves and keep all the money
so essentially the war was
the objective of the war was to ensure
that they don't have to pay taxes
anymore to the british king to the king
of england
so that is what it was it was a
separatist war it was the british
settlers in north america who wanted to
break their
ties with the british crown so that they
don't have to pay any more taxes so that
they can
get more money for for themselves
so it was british against british and
that's what it was
right let's take a couple more questions
um
what do we have
something that i've not answered before
how long does one session last well
let's find out
genie
what is the difference of what is the
history of afghans and the difference
between pathans and afghans
the pathans are the pashtuns
the majority population of afghanistan
is the pashtuns they are the true
inhabitants
of
afghanistan
they are genetically an extension of the
northern indian population
genetically culturally
they were
indians a thousand years ago
they are still genetically more or less
the same as the northern indian
population but culturally they are very
different now
so the history of afghanistan is a very
long history i can't tell you in two
minutes afghanistan was essentially
gandhar
a part of india
indian territory
and then things happened in the past
thousand years and it became a separate
country eventually
so the difference between pashtuns
pathans and afghans is that there is no
difference the majority
ethnic group in afghanistan is the
pashtuns
and i have other
videos about this i would recommend that
you watch that if you want to know more
who are the kalash people of pakistan
they are an ancient
ethnic group they look very european
but genetically they are indians
they practice a very ancient form of
hinduism which seems to be almost
rigvedic in
nature
they are extremely oppressed and
persecuted and
they may not last
very long in pakistan unfortunately
right
[Music]
any other questions that i have
that are interesting
what books do you suggest for
geopolitics lessons you know there are
no books for geopolitics
there are lots of books about various
kinds of history indian history western
history greek history roman history
african history american history blah
blah blah
geopolitics is something that transcends
all of these things there is no textbook
of geopolitics
you can't learn geopolitics from
textbooks
that's how it is i cannot suggest i
don't have a single book that i can
recommend or suggest for learning
geopolitics i have not learned
geopolitics from any textbook of
geopolitics that's not how it works
to understand geopolitics you have to
first understand causality
the cause and effect chain
that underlies the patterns of history
which means that you will study a lot of
history you do read a lot of world
history local history
then you understand the global system
the financial system
the supply chains so many more things
all of that if you understand then you
may understand understanding geopolitics
it's something that takes a lot of time
there is no course in any university on
geopolitics
or any any college
there are no textbooks so
unfortunately i am unable to recommend
books about geopolitics because no such
book exists
and i'm sure somebody some smart person
will now find some book that yeah there
is this textbook on geopolitics well
go ahead and read it and see how much
you learn
um
okay let me take one or two more
questions
okay ramad says
china claims vladimir japan when will
they open that issue if something
happens is the nuclear war possible
okay that's a good question let's go to
the map where is vladivostok
so this huge nation
in eurasia
from
europe all the way to asia is russia
in the west the capital is the capital
moscow
and this extends all the way to the
pacific ocean in the east
and
over here
where is the city vladivostok
here it is
so the city of vladivostok is a is a
port city it's a it's a coastal city
in the far east of russia it's right
north
of north korea
and the chinese
have a claim
they have always had claims to russian
parts of russian territory especially
the far east of russia
right now the claims
are dormant
the chinese and the russians
almost went to war in the 1960s
along the usuri river
and that almost led to a nuclear war it
was averted because of various reasons
which i've gone into in the past
so right now the territorial dispute is
more or less settled because they had
this agreement they signed the agreement
in the
about 20 or so years ago roughly
which closed the border issue
but the russians also understand that
any border dispute that they have with
the chinese
even if it may be officially settled
it's simply dormant the chinese will
bring it out when the time is right
so the chinese do claim by the water and
it is something that they will reopen in
the future when they deem the time to be
right
and that could lead to a war or maybe
not depending on the relative strengths
of the two nations at that point in time
so that's about the russia china border
dispute
vis-a-vis vladivostok
okay
shall we take
okay let's take one final question teja
says can ai help in archaeology
and deciphering unknown scripts ai can
certainly help in discovering unknown
scripts especially machine learning
you can feed a whole bunch of symbols
into the machine learning program and
see what it spits out as long as you
have trained it properly it may be
actually able to decipher
unknown scripts like
like the indus valley or the harappan or
the saraswati hindu script it is
certainly something that can help
and there is a program in which i mean
there is this
research program that i heard of a
couple of years ago
in which there is this ai that has been
trained to read egyptian hieroglyphics
and it's able to do
expedite the process of
translating previously untranslated
hieroglyphic inscriptions into english
so certainly it can be done it's already
being used for that kind of purpose
so maybe it is something we can use to
decipher the saraswati sindhu script
all right ladies and gentlemen thank you
very much for the questions i'm going to
stop it here i'm going to end it here
great doing this live again and we're
going to do it again next week
thank you very much thank you again to
all of all of you who have subscribed
thank you to my 300 000 fam strong
family
and i will see you next week until then
take care
and bye